Salutations, I’m Jesco and you’re watching
GameDevMadeEasy.
This is the final video that I will have made
while living in China!
In the video today, we are going to work with
DragonRuby.
(Record Scratch and crowd gasp)
DragonRuby is a game engine made using the
Ruby programming language.
(crowd groan)
Now hear me out, DragonRuby takes the minimalist
approach to game development and does not
rely on heavy usage of “magic” variables
or methods that is usually present with the
Ruby programming language.
So, you can get DragonRuby on itch.io or if
you are like me and found it on Reddit, the
links are in the description.
There are some pros and cons to the engine.
Pros are that it is very easy to pick up and
go with on any operating system, loads of
sample games and explanations, a beginner
and intermediate primer for the Ruby language
itself in the samples, and does not require
Ruby to be install on your machine to work
with the engine.
The cons are no intellisense for the built
in classes, and no documentation on the full
api for the engine.
There is however a basic explanation on the
DragonRuby itch page, but it doesn’t go
very in depth into this.
For the tutorial today, we are going to implement
a button from the ground up.
Before we can do that, we really have to understand
what a button actually is.
A button in its’ base form is a rectangle,
a label and a click event.
You can expand upon it by adding an image
to it and a mouse event for mouse over and
mouse off driving the image as well.
So after you have unzipped the DragonRuby
or dragonruby gtk lowrez folder.
Go inside the directory a bit further.
Go inside of the mygame folder.
Go inside of the app folder.
Double click to open main.rb in notepad++
or Visual Studio Code if you are on Windows.
For Mac, Atom, IntelliJ or Visual Studio Code
are your options.
We are going to delete everything from the
main.rb file.
A blank slate if you will.
Let’s begin by creating a class.
Write class Button.
This is similar to any other Object Oriented
language where we are defining out class.
Directly underneath it, with a tab space,
write attr_accessor.
This is an attribute that allows for us to
get and set instance variables.
Write colon outputs comma space colon inputs.
This allows for us to access the outputs and
inputs methods defined within the engine.
As you can probably guess, these handle i/o
and rendering.
Let’s go to a new line and write def Display
Button.
We are defining our first method of this class.
Now, let’s add parameters to it.
You can go with two different ways to handle
this.
The first way is to just write x comma y comma
text or the second way which is to add an
opening parenthesis x comma y comma text and
a closing parenthesis.
Both ways are valid in Ruby, I will go with
the parenthesis approach since I am used to
C style syntax.
As you can see, we aren’t defining the types
for these variables.
That is because Ruby is a dynamically typed
language, just like Python.
The x variable will be our x position, the
y variable will be our y position and the
text variable will be our string value.
The x and y will automatically be inferred
as an integer value unless we use floating
point values.
Press the enter button and in the next line
write button underscore border is set to be
square bracket x comma y comma 150 comma 150
comma 0 comma 0 comma 128 and closing square
bracket.
This is an array in Ruby and the values in
order by index is as followed: x position,
y position, width, height, red, green, blue.
On the next line write button underscore label
is set to open square bracket x plus 50 comma
y plus 75 comma text and closing square bracket.
The values for this array is x position, y
position and the text value.
On the next line, write outputs dot borders
with two greater than symbols button underscore
border.
This is saying that we are taking the output’s
borders and we want it to GET the place where
the border is defined which is the button
underscore border and request the new border
to be added from the definition.
On a new line, let’s do the same thing but
for the label.
Write outputs dot labels with two greater
than symbols and then write button underscore
label.
Now for the tricky part.
We are going to be registering our click events.
This will require a nested if statement because
we need to check for a regular click event
and then we need to check if the click event
happens within the border of our button.
To do this, we first need to start a new line
and then write.
If inputs dot mouse dot click.
This is just subscribing to listen for the
click event from the mouse.
On a new line, write if inputs dot mouse dot
click dot point dot inside underscore rect
with a question mark.
This if statement is checking if we are clicking
inside of the rectangle from an object that
is of the type rect.
The question mark designates that this is
nullable.
The last thing to do on this line is to write
button underscore border.
This will make the inside rectangle point
to our button border object.
On the next line write outputs dot labels
with two greater than symbols.
Write open square bracket 200 comma 300 comma
open quote clicked, closing quote and closing
square bracket.
This will generate a new label that will tell
us if the button was clicked or not.
We aren’t done here yet.
Write end four times.
This will be the terminators of the two if
statements we created, our display button
method and our class.
Ruby is very similar to Python in these regards.
Instead of semicolons, we have to use the
word end.
Visual Basic is similar to this as well.
That concludes the main bulk of this code.
As a matter of fact, the implementation details
are done, now we just have to define the tick
method for our main method that will call
this code and this will run as we intend it
to.
On a new line write def tick args.
This is our main update loop.
The args is just an informal name for arguments
which we will soon make heavy use of.
Write dollar sign button is set to be Button
dot new.
This creates an instance of the button class.
The dollar sign designates that this is a
global variable.
On a new line, write dollar sign button dot
outputs is set to be args dot outputs.
We are specifying that the attr underscore
accessor which called output is the same as
the arg’s outputs.
On the next line, write dollar sign button
dot inputs is set to be args dot inputs.
We are specifying that the attr underscore
accessor which called inputs is the same as
the arg’s inputs.
The final line is dollar sign button dot display
button.
The parameters are 500 comma 400 comma and
the string value of Click.
We are finally calling that display button
method we defined in the Button class and
setting the variables required for it.
Finally, write end.
Which again, designates that this is the end
of the method block.
There we have it, you can click on the DragonRuby
dot exe file or the DragonRuby file specific
for Mac or Linux.
It will run the program and if you click inside
of the button, it will quickly flash the text
telling us that this code worked correctly.
As a Challenge for you guys, go through the
samples for DragonRuby and try to figure out
how to add images to the Display button method,
make it so after clicking that the text will
stay shown while the button is being pressed
and fix the alignment bug that is present
on the text if you use longer text phrases.
Thank you all for watching and I’ll see
you guys when I return to the USA in the next
few days where I will be able to record more
content for you guys and showcase my solution
to the challenge asked of you guys.
https://www.reddit.com/r/learnprogramming/comments/clbm3t/build_a_game_to_learn_how_to_program_dammit_im/
https://dragonruby.itch.io/dragonruby-gtk